<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Uncategorized Archives - Sage Builders</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/uncategorized/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/category/uncategorized/</link>
	<description>General Contracting Service</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2019 08:40:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>5 Ways Refinancing Your Home Loan Can Help You</title>
		<link>/5-ways-refinancing-your-home-loan-can-help-you/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[andrew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2019 08:40:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://sage.decibeldevelopment.com/?p=7543</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We take a look at 5 ways refinancing your home loan could help you: 1. Your lender&#8217;s rate is no [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/5-ways-refinancing-your-home-loan-can-help-you/">5 Ways Refinancing Your Home Loan Can Help You</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Sage Builders</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>We take a look at 5 ways refinancing your home loan could help you:</strong></p>



<p><strong>1. Your lender&#8217;s rate is no longer competitive</strong></p>



<p>We&#8217;ll
 start with the popular one first. One of the main reasons people choose
 to refinance their loan is to get a lower interest rate, and put more 
money back into their pockets instead of paying the banks.</p>



<p>When done correctly, refinancing your home loan could save you thousands over the life of your loan, and free up cash now.</p>



<p><strong>2. You could switch between variable &amp; fixed rates</strong></p>



<p>Another
 popular reason to refinance your home loan is to switch between a 
variable rate and a fixed rate. With a fixed rate, some want peace of 
mind. That is, knowing exactly how much their monthly repayments will be
 without the possibility of it changing for a set period is worth a 
slight increase in rate.</p>



<p>Conversely, you may decide you&#8217;d like to 
take advantage of a lower variable rate as you can accept the risk that 
rates may rise in future.</p>



<p><strong>3. You could be eligible for a home loan with better features</strong></p>



<p>There
 are some great home loan features around at the moment, and refinancing
 could offer you the opportunity to take advantage or more flexible 
features. Some money saving features to look for are:</p>



<p><strong>Flexible repayments</strong>:
 You might want to switch to a home loan that allows you to make lump 
repayments without fees or open up an offset account to reduce your 
interest.</p>



<p><strong>Redraw: </strong>Allows you to withdraw extra payments if you need cash. Look for a loan offering free redraws.</p>



<p>There
 are also some pretty cool boutique features, like getting a repayment 
holiday (a break from repayments), or the loan portability which allows 
you to take your home loan with you when you move without much hassle.</p>



<p><strong>4. You could consolidate your debt</strong></p>



<p>Many
 of us have multiple debts like car or credit card along with our home 
loan. Often our car and credit card loans have pretty high interest 
rates, meaning more out of your pocket.</p>



<p>Refinancing could give you
 the opportunity to merge your debts and potentially reduce the overall 
interest you&#8217;re paying, streamlining all of higher interest debts into 
one lower interest debt and reducing your monthly repayments.</p>



<p>The 
interest rate on a home loan is usually significantly lower than the 
other types of credit. Helping you to save on interest charges and pay 
debt off sooner.</p>



<p><strong>5. You could release some equity in your current property</strong></p>



<p>You
 may be thinking about joining the thousands of Australians that have 
invested in property, renovating your home or traipsing around Europe on
 that trip of a lifetime. With your current home usually being your most
 valuable asset, it only makes sense to release as much of the value in 
your home as possible.</p>



<p>Home equity is the difference between your 
home&#8217;s current value and the balance of your mortgage. For example, if 
your home is worth $600,000 and you have a mortgage of $200,000 
remaining, your home equity is $400,000. That&#8217;s money that can be used 
to build wealth.</p>



<p>Not so long ago, the only way home owners could 
access their home equity was to sell up and upgrade to another property.
 These days, home loans are flexible and it&#8217;s possible to get access to 
the equity in your home without having to sell up. Reviewing your home 
loan can help you see exactly how much equity is available to you, and 
refinancing can help you access the equity to use for other things.</p>



<p><strong>What should I consider before refinancing?</strong></p>



<p><strong>Cost of refinancing</strong></p>



<p>While
 refinancing has some amazing benefits, there are costs associated with 
refinancing your home loan &#8211; costs that may outweigh the potential 
benefits. Following are two of the main costs associated with 
refinancing:</p>



<p><strong>Exit Fees</strong></p>



<p>Exit fees may apply 
when you pay out a loan early, usually in the first three to five years 
of your term. It could be a percentage of the remaining loan balance or 
it may be a set charge. Check your loan contract for more details. 
Although exit fees have been banned on new loans taken out after 1 July 
2011, they could still apply to loans taken out before this date.</p>



<p><strong>Borrowing costs</strong></p>



<p>When
 you refinance, your new lender may charge a range of upfront fees. 
However not all lenders charge these fees and some may be negotiable.</p>



<p><strong>Case Study</strong></p>



<p>Let&#8217;s have a look at a refinancing example using some numbers to better understand the benefits and costs.</p>



<p><strong>The situation:</strong></p>



<p>Sue has a $300,000 loan repayable over 25 years. Her current rate is 6.4% and her monthly repayments are $2,006.</p>



<p>If
 Sue can refinance to a loan with a rate of 5.9% a rate reduction of 
0.50%, she can lower her repayments to $1,914, a saving of $92 each 
month.</p>



<p><strong>The solution:</strong></p>



<p>Looking at the cost 
side of things, we&#8217;ll assume Sue will pay $1,000 to refinance her loan. 
In this case it would take about 11 months ($1,000 divided by $92) for 
Sue to claw back the costs through the savings she makes.</p>



<p><strong>The outcome:</strong></p>



<p>That&#8217;s not a bad time frame. If it was to take several years to recover her costs, refinancing may not be worthwhile.</p>



<p><strong>Should you refinance?</strong></p>



<p>We&#8217;ve
 gone through the potential benefits of refinancing, the costs 
associated and a short example. That&#8217;s a lot to take in. When it comes 
time to make a decision about refinancing your home loan, the best 
suggestion is to sit down with a mortgage broker you trust to help you 
go through your options.</p>



<p>

Article Source: http://EzineArticles.com/9899507<br></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/5-ways-refinancing-your-home-loan-can-help-you/">5 Ways Refinancing Your Home Loan Can Help You</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Sage Builders</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Make Your Smart Home &#8220;Smarter&#8221;</title>
		<link>/how-to-make-your-smart-home-smarter/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[andrew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2019 08:38:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://sage.decibeldevelopment.com/?p=7540</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>With the way technology works these days, owning a smart home has become even more exciting. From your home&#8217;s lighting, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/how-to-make-your-smart-home-smarter/">How to Make Your Smart Home &#8220;Smarter&#8221;</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Sage Builders</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>With
 the way technology works these days, owning a smart home has become 
even more exciting. From your home&#8217;s lighting, temperature control and 
even safety, the devices you can add are almost limitless. These things 
can easily make you want to keep adding more. If you already own a smart
 home and are currently thinking of upgrading it, here&#8217;s a quick rundown
 of what you need to do to make your smart home &#8220;smarter.&#8221;</p>



<p><strong>Add Voice-Controlled Devices</strong></p>



<p>Formerly,
 voice-controlled devices could only play music. Now, there are 
voice-controlled devices that can act as your assistants. They can set 
your alarms, control your lights and even give you directions, even 
without pressing any buttons. Some of these devices can even alert you 
if anything unusual happens at home.</p>



<p><strong>Install Smart Lighting</strong></p>



<p>Automating
 your lights can slash a huge portion of your electricity bill. Pair 
them with sensors, dimmers and wireless control and you&#8217;ll be able to 
save even more. You can set your lights to turn on and off, depending on
 your personal schedule or, add motion sensors, so you won&#8217;t waste 
energy. You can even use your smartphone to control the brightness, 
color as well as the ambiance of your home.</p>



<p>If your smart phone 
isn&#8217;t enough, you can install a smart device that can notify you when 
you have left your lights on. Apart from the alerts, this device can 
also give you an estimate of how much energy your home has already 
consumed.</p>



<p><strong>Secure Your Router</strong></p>



<p>When you&#8217;re 
building a smart home, your concern shouldn&#8217;t be limited to the kinds of
 devices you&#8217;ll invest in; you also have to take proper measures on how 
you&#8217;ll secure everything inside it. Your router is one of your home&#8217;s 
weakest spots. Much like your front door, you should strengthen it to 
keep intruders out.</p>



<p>Start by changing your password. As soon as 
you receive your router, change its default password with something that
 can&#8217;t easily be guessed. Refrain from using your birth year or the last
 digits of your phone number. As much as possible, create a lengthy 
password and make sure to use alphanumeric characters to make it even 
harder to crack.</p>



<p>It&#8217;s also a good idea to constantly upgrade your 
security software to decrease your devices&#8217; vulnerability to new 
threats, like spying tools and viruses. Install a malware protection to 
prevent suspicious and malicious programs from running on your computer.</p>



<p><strong>Upgrade Your Smoke Detector</strong></p>



<p>An
 ordinary smoke detector that gets activated can cause confusion, 
especially if you have several units at home. If it isn&#8217;t monitored, 
there&#8217;s no way you&#8217;ll get alerted about a possible fire &#8211; unless you 
have some friendly neighbors looking after your home. For your safety 
and security, it&#8217;s best if you can upgrade your smoke detector to 
something smarter.</p>



<p>Most smart smoke detectors today are industrial
 grade and can last a long time. Some of them even come with dedicated 
apps to help make monitoring a lot easier. Apart from battery life, they
 can also tell you exactly which area of the house is showing increased 
temperature. They can even connect you to your local police and firemen 
for a quick resolution.</p>



<p>These extra features can mean a higher 
price tag. However, considering that they can augment your home security
 and initiate a faster response, they can be considered as valuable 
investments.</p>



<p>If you are on a tight budget and investing in new 
devices doesn&#8217;t seem feasible at the moment, your next best option is to
 invest in a device that can turn ordinary devices into smart ones.</p>



<p><strong>Get a Smart Doorbell</strong></p>



<p>As
 home automation becomes even more sophisticated, you&#8217;ll find yourself 
being able to do the things that seemed impossible before. Take, for 
example, answering your door, even if you&#8217;re not physically at home.</p>



<p>You&#8217;ll
 be able to tell the delivery man where to leave your parcel or check on
 someone who&#8217;s been showing interest in your front gate for several 
days. Burglars favor houses that are unoccupied. By being able to answer
 the door and show that you can see what&#8217;s happening around your 
property, you&#8217;ll be able to make your home a lot less favorable for 
burglary.</p>



<p>Smart doorbells can do so much more than that, 
especially when they are equipped with the right features. With night 
vision capabilities, live streaming and a two-way talk feature, you&#8217;ll 
be able to detect intruders and burglars even before they execute their 
plans. You can even record videos to serve as hard evidence in case 
someone manages to get inside your property.</p>



<p>Also, by monitoring 
your feed, you can check on your kids and know when they arrive home 
safely from school. You can also get alerts whenever they leave the 
house without your permission.</p>



<p><strong>Over To You</strong></p>



<p>How
 Smart is your Home? Have you upgraded all your security devices and 
installed new ones available in the market? Have you made your home 
&#8220;safe enough&#8221;? I would give this a second thought and re-visit all the 
points mentioned above to have a stress-free life without having to 
worry about your home safety.</p>



<p>

Article Source: http://EzineArticles.com/9973153<br></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/how-to-make-your-smart-home-smarter/">How to Make Your Smart Home &#8220;Smarter&#8221;</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Sage Builders</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Home Inspections &#8211; A Question and Answer Guide</title>
		<link>/home-inspections-a-question-and-answer-guide/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[andrew]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2019 08:36:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://sage.decibeldevelopment.com/?p=7537</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A home inspection is an evaluation of the visible and accessible systems and components of a home (plumbing, heating and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/home-inspections-a-question-and-answer-guide/">Home Inspections &#8211; A Question and Answer Guide</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Sage Builders</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>A  home inspection is an evaluation of the visible and accessible systems  and components of a home (plumbing, heating and cooling, electrical,  structure, roof, etc.) and is intended to give the client (buyer,  seller, or homeowner) a better understanding of the home&#8217;s general  condition. Most often it is a buyer who requests an inspection of the  home he or she is serious about purchasing</p>



<p>. A home inspection delivers  data so that decisions about the purchase can be confirmed or  questioned, and can uncover serious and/or expensive to repair defects  that the seller/owner may not be aware of. It is not an appraisal of the  property&#8217;s value; nor does it address the cost of repairs. It does not  guarantee that the home complies with local building codes or protect a  client in the event an item inspected fails in the future. [Note:  Warranties can be purchased to cover many items.] A home inspection  should not be considered a &#8220;technically exhaustive&#8221; evaluation, but  rather an evaluation of the property on the day it is inspected, taking  into consideration normal wear and tear for the home&#8217;s age and location.  A home inspection can also include, for extra fees, Radon gas testing,  water testing, energy audits, pest inspections, pool inspections, and  several other specific items that may be indigenous to the region of the  country where the inspection takes place. Home inspections are also  used (less often) by a seller before listing the property to see if  there are any hidden problems that they are unaware of, and also by  homeowners simply wishing to care for their homes, prevent surprises,  and keep the home investment value as high as possible.</p>



<p>The important results to pay attention to in a home inspection are:</p>



<p>1.
 Major defects, such as large differential cracks in the foundation; 
structure out of level or plumb; decks not installed or supported 
properly, etc. These are items that are expensive to fix, which we 
classify as items requiring more than 2% of the purchase price to 
repair.</p>



<p>2. Things that could lead to major defects &#8211; a roof 
flashing leak that could get bigger, damaged downspouts that could cause
 backup and water intrusion, or a support beam that was not tied in to 
the structure properly.</p>



<p>3. Safety hazards, such as an exposed 
electrical wiring, lack of GFCI (Ground Fault Circuit Interrupters) in 
kitchens and bathrooms, lack of safety railing on decks more than 30 
inches off the ground, etc.</p>



<p>Your inspector will advise you about 
what to do about these problems. He/she may recommend evaluation &#8211; and 
on serious issues most certainly will &#8211; by licensed or certified 
professionals who are specialists in the defect areas. For example, your
 inspector will recommend you call a licensed building engineer if they 
find sections of the home that are out of alignment, as this could 
indicate a serious structural deficiency.</p>



<p><strong>Home Inspections are only done by a buyer after they sign a contract, right?</strong></p>



<p>This
 is not true! As you will see when you read on, a home inspection can be
 used for interim inspections in new construction, as a maintenance tool
 by a current homeowner, a proactive technique by sellers to make their 
home more sellable, and by buyers wanting to determine the condition of 
the potential home.</p>



<p>Sellers, in particular, can benefit from 
getting a home inspection before listing the home. Here are just a few 
of the advantages for the seller:</p>



<p>· The seller knows the home! The
 home inspector will be able to get answers to his/her questions on the 
history of any problems they find.</p>



<p>· A home inspection will help the seller be more objective when it comes to setting a fair price on the home.</p>



<p>· The seller can take the report and make it into a marketing piece for the home.</p>



<p>· The seller will be alerted to any safety issues found in the home before they open it up for open house tours.</p>



<p>· The seller can make repairs leisurely instead being in a rush after the contract is signed.</p>



<p><strong>Why should I get a home inspection? </strong></p>



<p>Your
 new home has dozens of systems and over 10,000 parts &#8211; from heating and
 cooling to ventilation and appliances. When these systems and 
appliances work together, you experience comfort, energy savings, and 
durability. Weak links in the system, however, can produce assorted 
problems leading to a loss in value and shortened component life. Would 
you buy a used car without a qualified mechanic looking at it? Your home
 is far more complicated, and to have a thorough inspection that is 
documented in a report arms you with substantial information on which to
 make decisions.</p>



<p><strong>Why can&#8217;t I do the inspection myself?</strong></p>



<p>Most
 homebuyers lack the knowledge, skill, and objectivity needed to inspect
 a home themselves. By using the services of a professional home 
inspector, they gain a better understanding of the condition of the 
property; especially whether any items do not &#8220;function as intended&#8221; or 
&#8220;adversely affect the habitability of the dwelling&#8221; or &#8220;warrant further 
investigation&#8221; by a specialist. Remember that the home inspector is a 
generalist and is broadly trained in every home system.</p>



<p><strong>Why can&#8217;t I ask a family member who is handy or who is a contractor to inspect my new home?</strong></p>



<p>Although
 your nephew or aunt may be very skilled, he or she is not trained or 
experienced in professional home inspections and usually lacks the 
specialized test equipment and knowledge required for an inspection. 
Home inspection training and expertise represent a distinct, licensed 
profession that employs rigorous standards of practice. Most contractors
 and other trade professionals hire a professional home inspector to 
inspect their own homes when they themselves purchase a home!</p>



<p><strong>What does a home inspection cost?</strong></p>



<p>This
 is often the first question asked but the answer tells the least about 
the quality of the inspection. Fees are based according to size, age and
 various other aspects of the home. Inspection fees from a certified 
professional home inspector generally start under $300. An average price
 for a 2,000 square foot home nationally is about $350-$375. What you 
should pay attention to is not the fee, but the qualifications of your 
inspector. Are they nationally certified (passed the NHIE exam)? Are 
they state certified if required?</p>



<p><strong>How long does the inspection take?</strong></p>



<p>This
 depends upon the size and condition of the home. You can usually figure
 1.2 hours for every 1,000 square feet. For example, a 2,500 square foot
 house would take about 3 hours. If the company also produces the report
 at your home, that will take an additional 30-50 minutes.</p>



<p><strong>Do all homes require a home inspection?</strong></p>



<p>Yes
 and No. Although not required by law in most states, we feel that any 
buyer not getting a home inspection is doing themselves a great 
disservice. They may find themselves with costly and unpleasant 
surprises after moving into the home and suffer financial headaches that
 could easily have been avoided.</p>



<p><strong>Should I be at the inspection? </strong></p>



<p>It&#8217;s
 a great idea for you be present during the inspection &#8211; whether you are
 buyer, seller, or homeowner. With you there, the inspector can show you
 any defects and explain their importance as well as point out 
maintenance features that will be helpful in the future. If you can&#8217;t be
 there, it is not a problem since the report you receive will be very 
detailed. If you are not present, then you should be sure to ask your 
inspector to explain anything that is not clear in the report. Also read
 the inspection agreement carefully so you understand what is covered 
and what is not covered in the inspection. If there is a problem with 
the inspection or the report, you should raise the issues quickly by 
calling the inspector, usually within 24 hours. If you want the 
inspector to return after the inspection to show you things, this can be
 arranged and is a good idea, however, you will be paying for the 
inspector&#8217;s time on a walkthrough since this was not included in the 
original service.</p>



<p>Should the seller attend the home inspection that has been ordered by the buyer?</p>



<p>The
 seller will be welcome at the inspection (it is still their home) 
although they should understand that the inspector is working for the 
buyer. The conversation that the inspector has with the buyer may be 
upsetting to the seller if the seller was unaware of the items being 
pointed out, or the seller may be overly emotional about any flaws. This
 is a reason why the seller might want to consider getting their own 
inspection before listing the home.</p>



<p>Can a house fail a home inspection?</p>



<p>No.
 A home inspection is an examination of the current condition of your 
prospective home. It is not an appraisal, which determines market value,
 or a municipal inspection, which verifies local code compliance. A home
 inspector, therefore, cannot not pass or fail a house. The inspector 
will objectively describe the home&#8217;s physical condition and indicate 
which items are in need of repair or replacement.</p>



<p><strong>What is included in the inspection?</strong></p>



<p>The
 following list is not exhaustive. Not all of these may be in the 
inspection you get, but the inspector will be following a standardized 
checklist for the home:
<br>· Site drainage and grading
<br>· Driveway
<br>· Entry Steps, handrails
<br>· Decks
<br>· Masonry
<br>· Landscape (as it relates to the home)
<br>· Retaining walls
<br>· Roofing, flashings, chimneys, and attic
<br>· Eaves, soffits, and fascias
<br>· Walls, doors, windows, patios, walkways
<br>· Foundation, basement, and crawlspaces
<br>· Garage, garage walls, floor, and door operation
<br>· Kitchen appliances (dishwasher, range/oven/cooktop/hoods, microwave, disposal, trash compactor)
<br>· Laundry appliances (washer and dryer)
<br>· Ceilings, walls, floors
<br>· Kitchen counters, floors, and cabinets
<br>· Windows and window gaskets
<br>· Interior doors and hardware
<br>· Plumbing systems and fixtures
<br>· Electrical system, panels, entrance conductors
<br>· Electrical grounding, GFCI, outlets
<br>· Smoke (fire) detectors
<br>· Ventilation systems and Insulation
<br>· Heating equipment and controls
<br>· Ducts and distribution systems
<br>· Fireplaces
<br>· Air Conditioning and controls
<br>· Heat Pumps and controls
<br>· Safety items such as means of egress, TPRV valves, railings, etc.</p>



<p>Other items that are not a part of the standard inspection can be added for an additional fee:
<br>· Radon Gas Test
<br>· Water Quality Test
<br>· Termite Inspection (usually performed by a separate company)
<br>· Gas Line Leak Test (usually performed by the gas company)
<br>· Sprinkler System Test
<br>· Swimming Pool and Spa Inspection
<br>· Mold Screening (sometimes performed by a separate company)
<br>· Septic System Inspection (usually performed by a separate company)
<br>· Alarm System (usually performed by a separate company)</p>



<p>We 
recommend getting a Radon Test if your prospective home falls into an 
area of the country with known Radon seepage, since Radon gas produces 
cancer second only to cigarette smoking and can be easily mitigated by 
installing a vent system. We also recommend a water test to make sure 
you do not have bacteria in the water supply. Water can also be tested 
for Radon.</p>



<p><strong>What is not included in the inspection?</strong></p>



<p>Most
 people assume that everything is inspected in depth on inspection day. 
This misunderstanding has caused many a homebuyer to be upset with their
 inspector. The inspections we do are not exhaustive and there is a good
 reason for this. If you hired someone with licenses for heating and 
cooling, electrical, plumbing, engineering, etc. to inspect your house, 
it would take about 14 hours and cost you about $2000! It is much more 
practical to hire a professional inspector who has generalist knowledge 
of home systems, knows what to look for, and can recommend further 
inspection by a specialist if needed. Your inspector is also following 
very specific guidelines as he/she inspects your home. These are either 
national guidelines (ASHI &#8211; American Society of Home Inspectors, 
InterNACHI &#8211; International Association of Certified Home Inspectors) or 
state guidelines. These guidelines are carefully written to protect both
 your home and the inspector. Here are some examples: We are directed to
 not turn systems on if they were off at the time of the inspection 
(safety reasons); we are not allowed to move furniture (might harm 
something); not allowed to turn on water if it is off (possible 
flooding), and not allowed to break through a sealed attic hatch 
(possible damage). The downside of this practice is that by not 
operating a control, by not seeing under the furniture, and not getting 
into the attic or crawlspace, we will might miss identifying a problem. 
However, put into perspective, the chances of missing something serious 
because of this is quite low, and the guideline as it relates to safety 
and not harming anything in the home is a good one. There are other 
items that 95% of inspectors consider outside a normal inspection, and 
these include inspecting most things that are not bolted down (installed
 in the home) such as electronics, low voltage lighting, space heaters, 
portable air conditioners, or specialized systems such as water 
purifiers, alarm systems, etc.</p>



<p><strong>What if there are things you can&#8217;t inspect (like snow on the roof)?</strong></p>



<p>It
 just so happens that some days the weather elements interfere with a 
full home inspection! There isn&#8217;t much we can do about this either. If 
there is snow on the roof we will tell you we were unable to inspect it.
 Of course we will be looking at the eves and the attic, and any other 
areas where we can get an idea of condition, but we will write in the 
report that we could not inspect the roof. It is impractical for us to 
return another day once the snow melts, because we have full schedules. 
However, you can usually pay an inspector a small fee to return and 
inspect the one or two items they were unable to inspect when they were 
there the first time. This is just the way things go. If you ask the 
inspector for a re-inspection, they will usually inspect the items then at no extra charge (beyond the re-inspection fee).</p>



<p><strong>Will the inspector walk on the roof?</strong></p>



<p>The
 inspector will walk on the roof if it is safe, accessible, and strong 
enough so that there is no damage done to it by walking on it. Some 
roofs &#8211; such as slate and tile, should not be walked on. Sometimes 
because of poor weather conditions, extremely steep roofs, or very high 
roofs, the inspector will not be able to walk the roof. The inspector 
will try to get up to the edge though, and will also use binoculars 
where accessibility is a problem. They will also examine the roof from 
the upper windows if that is possible. There is a lot the inspector can 
determine from a visual examination from a ladder and from the ground, 
and they will be able to tell a lot more from inside the attic about the
 condition of the roof as well.</p>



<p><strong>Should I have my house tested for Radon? What exactly is Radon?</strong></p>



<p>In
 many areas of the country, the answer is a definite yes. You can ask 
your real estate agent about this or go on to the internet for a radon 
map of the country. Radon is a colorless, odorless, tasteless 
radioactive gas that&#8217;s formed during the natural breakdown of uranium in
 soil, rock, and water. Radon exits the ground and can seep into your 
home through cracks and holes in the foundation. Radon gas can also 
contaminate well water.</p>



<p>Health officials have determined that 
radon gas is a serious carcinogen that can cause lung cancer, second 
only to cigarette smoking. The only way to find out if your house 
contains radon gas is to perform a radon measurement test, which your 
home inspector can do. Make sure the person conducting your test has 
been trained to The National Environmental Health Association (NEHA) or 
The National Radon Safety Board (NRSB) standards.</p>



<p><strong>What about a newly constructed home? Does it need a home inspection?</strong></p>



<p>Yes!
 In fact, we find far more problems, some quite serious, in newly 
constructed homes than in homes that have been lived in for years. This 
is not due to your builder&#8217;s negligence &#8211; he/she has done the best job 
they could with subcontractors and planning &#8211; it&#8217;s just that there are 
so many systems in a home, that it is close to impossible to inspect 
everything, and correct it before the Certificate of Occupancy is 
issued. Then, for some reason, the subcontractors no longer want to work
 on the home, and final jobs and details are missed. We recommend 
getting several professional home inspections near the completion stages
 of the home to discover everything that should be corrected. If the 
house is still new but sitting for a while before sale, it&#8217;s even more 
important to get a home inspection. We have seen water lines not hooked 
up, plumbing lines not hooked up, sewer lines not hooked up, vents not 
hooked up, and a variety of other serious but easily correctable 
problems!</p>



<p><strong>I am having a home built. The builder assures me he 
will inspect everything. Should I have an independent inspector make 
periodic inspections?</strong></p>



<p>Absolutely yes! No matter how good your 
builder is, he/she WILL miss things. They are so concerned with the 
house, they get so close to their work, as do the subcontractors, that 
important items can, and will be, overlooked. Have a professional 
inspector make at least 4-6 interim inspections. They will be worth 
their weight in gold.</p>



<p><strong>What is the Pre-Inspection Agreement?</strong></p>



<p>Most
 service professionals have a service agreement, and home inspection is 
no different. In fact, there is enough confusion about what a home 
inspection should deliver that the agreement is even more important. 
Some homeowners who get a home inspection expect everything in the home 
to be perfect after the repairs. This is not the case! Imagine getting a
 call from a homeowner a year later who says the toilet is not flushing &#8211;
 remember that the inspection is a moment in time snapshot. In the 
inspection agreement the inspector is clear about what the inspection 
delivers and the things that are not covered, as well as what you should
 do if you are not pleased with the services. We really think that by 
reviewing this before-hand you will understand much more about the 
inspection and be happier with the results. A home inspection does not 
guard against future problems, nor does it guarantee that all problems 
will be found.</p>



<p><strong>What kind of report will I get following the inspection?</strong></p>



<p>There
 are as many versions of a &#8220;report&#8221; as there are inspection companies. 
Guidelines dictate that the inspector deliver a written report to the 
client. This can range from a handwritten checklist that has multiple 
press copies without pictures and 4 pages long to a computer generated 
professionally produced report with digital pictures that is 35 pages 
long and can be converted to Adobe PDF for storage and emailing. Be sure
 to check with your inspector about the report he or she uses. We 
recommend the computer generated report, since the checklist is more 
detailed and easier for the homeowner/buyer/seller to detail out the 
issues with photographs. In this modern age, we feel the reports must be
 web accessible and e-mailable to match the technologies most of us are 
using.</p>



<p>There are some great things you can use the report for in 
addition to the wealth of information it simply gives you on your new 
home:</p>



<p>· Use the report as a checklist and guide for the contractor
 to make repairs and improvements or get estimates and quotes from more 
than one contractor.</p>



<p>· Use the report as a budgeting tool using 
the inspector&#8217;s recommendations and the remaining expected life of 
components to keep the property in top shape.</p>



<p>· If you are a 
seller, use the report to make repairs and improvements, raising the 
value of the home and impressing the buyers. Then have a re-inspection 
and use this second report as a marketing tool for prospective buyers.</p>



<p>· Use the report as a &#8220;punch list&#8221; on a re-inspection and as a baseline for ongoing maintenance.</p>



<p><strong>Will the report be emailable or available as an Adobe PDF file?</strong></p>



<p>Yes. As discussed in the last question, you will probably want your inspector to be using the latest reporting technology.</p>



<p><strong>What if I think the inspector missed something?</strong></p>



<p>Inspectors
 are human, and yes, they do miss items. However, they routinely use 
advanced tools and techniques to reduce the possibility that they will 
miss something. This includes very detailed checklists, reference 
manuals, computer based lists, and a methodical always-done-the-same-way
 of physically moving around your home. That is one of the reasons that 
an inspector can miss an item when they get interrupted. The inspector 
will have a set way of resuming the inspection if this happens. If, in 
the end, something IS missed, call the inspector and discuss it. It may 
warrant the inspector returning to view something that you found. 
Remember, the inspector is doing the very best job they know how to do, 
and probably did not miss the item because they were lax in their 
technique or did not care.</p>



<p><strong>What if the inspector tells me I 
should have a professional engineer or a licensed plumber or other 
professional contractor in to look at something they found? Isn&#8217;t this 
&#8220;passing the buck&#8221;?</strong></p>



<p>You may be disappointed that further 
investigation is required, but, believe us, your inspector is doing 
exactly what they should be doing. The purpose of the inspection is to 
discover defects that affect your safety and the functioning of the 
home; the inspector is a generalist, not a specialist. Our code of 
ethics as well as national and state guidelines dictate that only 
contractors that are licensed in their specialty field should 
work on these systems and areas. When they tell you that a specialist is
 needed, there may be a bigger, more critical issue that you need to 
know about. If you move into the home without getting these areas 
checked by a qualified specialist, you could be in for some nasty and 
expensive surprises. The inspector does not want to cause you any more 
expense or worry either, so when they do recommend further evaluation 
they are being serious about protecting you and your investment.</p>



<p><strong>Will the inspector provide a warranty on the inspected items?</strong></p>



<p>Most
 inspectors do not give the homeowner a warranty on inspected items. 
Remember, a home inspection is a visual examination on a certain day, 
and the inspector cannot predict what issues could arise over time after
 the inspection. However, some inspectors are now including a warranty 
from the largest home warranty company in America &#8211; American Home 
Warranty Corporation, as well as others, on the inspected items for 60 
or 90 days. This is a very good deal, and the agreement can be extended 
after the initial period for a relatively small amount of money.</p>



<p><strong>Do most inspection companies offer money back guarantees?</strong></p>



<p>Most
 inspection companies do not offer a satisfaction guarantee nor do they 
mention it in their advertising. It&#8217;s always a good thing if you can get
 extra services for no additional cost from your inspection company, and
 of course a satisfaction guarantee is an indication of superior 
customer service. You usually have to call your inspection company right
 after the inspection and viewing of the report to tell them you are not
 satisfied. If you are not happy with the services, you should talk to 
your inspector first and let him/her correct the issue(s) you are 
unhappy with first, as the inspector is trying to make an honest living 
just like the rest of us, and is not failing you on purpose.</p>



<p><strong>What if my report comes back with nothing really defective in the home? Should I ask for my money back?</strong></p>



<p>No,
 don&#8217;t ask for your money back &#8211; you just received great news! Now you 
can complete your home purchase with peace of mind about the condition 
of the property and all its equipment and systems. You will have 
valuable information about your new home from the inspector&#8217;s report, 
and will want to keep that information for future reference. Most 
importantly, you can feel assured that you are making a well-informed 
purchase decision.</p>



<p><strong>What if the inspection reveals serious defects?</strong></p>



<p>If
 the inspection reveals serious defects in the home (we define a serious
 defect as something that will cost more than 2% of the purchase price 
to fix) then pat yourself on the back for getting an inspection. You 
just saved yourself a ton of money. Of course it is disappointing, even 
heart wrenching, to find out that your well researched house is now a 
problem house, but you now know the facts and can either negotiate with 
the seller, or move on. You may want the home so much that it will be 
worth it to negotiate the price and then perform the repairs. Imagine, 
though, if you had not gotten the inspection &#8211; you would have had some 
very unpleasant surprises.</p>



<p><strong>Can I ask my home inspector to perform the repairs?</strong></p>



<p>You
 can, but if your inspector is ethical, he/she will refuse, and 
correctly so; it is a conflict of interest for the person who inspected 
your home to also repair it! Inspectors are specifically barred from 
this practice by licensing authorities, and it&#8217;s a good practice &#8211; an 
inspector must remain completely impartial when he or she inspects your 
home. This is one reason you should have a professional home inspector 
inspect your home and not a contractor &#8211; the contractor will want the 
repair work and you are likely to not have an objective inspection from 
this person even though they mean well and are technically competent.</p>



<p><strong>Does the Seller have to make the repairs?</strong></p>



<p>The
 inspection report results do not place an obligation on the seller to 
repair everything mentioned in the report. Once the home condition is 
known, the buyer and the seller should sit down and discuss what is in 
the report. The report will be clear about what is a repair and what is a
 discretionary improvement. This area should be clearly negotiated 
between the parties. It&#8217;s important to know that the inspector must stay
 out of this discussion because it is outside of their scope of work.</p>



<p><strong>After
 the home inspection and consulting with the seller on the repairs, can I
 re-employ the inspector to come re-inspect the home to make sure 
everything got fixed?</strong></p>



<p>You certainly can, and it&#8217;s a really 
good idea. For a small fee the inspector will return to determine if the
 repairs were completed, and if they were completed correctly.</p>



<p><strong>What if I find problems after I move into my new home? </strong></p>



<p>A
 home inspection is not a guarantee that problems won&#8217;t develop after 
you move in. However, if you believe that a problem was visible at the 
time of the inspection and should have been mentioned in the report, 
your first step should be to call the inspector. He or she will be fine 
with this, and does want you to call if you think there is a problem. If
 the issue is not resolved with a phone call, they will come to your 
home to look at it. They will want you to be satisfied and will do 
everything they can to do this. One way to protect yourself between the 
inspection and the move-in is to conduct a final walkthrough on closing 
day and use both the inspection report AND a Walkthrough Checklist to 
make sure everything is as it should be.<br></p>



<p>Copyright 2010 by Lisa P. Turner</p>



<p>

Article Source: http://EzineArticles.com/3618814<br></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/home-inspections-a-question-and-answer-guide/">Home Inspections &#8211; A Question and Answer Guide</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Sage Builders</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
